So hopefully everyone's having a good
time with assignment one. Uh it's due
tonight. Uh let us know if you need an
extension. Assignment due two is uh
coming out soon. We're putting on the
finishing touches onto some of the the
Triton stuff. Um hopefully you'll enjoy
it. You'll get to implement um Flash
Attention 2 or parts of Flash Attention
2 which I think will be nice.
So today we're going to talk about uh
GPUs. GPUs are the thing that makes our
language models go. So they're pretty
critical to get right. Um and if you
haven't really studied, you know, the
hardware that makes you know your models
run, they can seem pretty mysterious. So
my goal today is to try to make CUDA and
GPUs less magic. Um and one of the
things that I want to demystify, you
don't have to understand the plot.
There's a there's a lot on the slide I
know. Um you know why do GPUs get slow?
And they get slow in very mysterious
ways. You know I will try to talk
through this plot um near towards the
end of lecture. As you increase the size
of your matrix multiplies you might
expect you know either gets slower or
faster or whatever you get these very
unpredictable looking wavelike patterns
and you're like why is my GPU fast at
certain multiples of certain numbers and
slow at others? Right? It's very
mysterious. We'll try to understand
that. The other thing is we would like
to understand how to make fast
algorithms. Um I think almost all of you
have heard of flash attention. Um it's
the thing that makes you know much
longer context possible by very cleverly
computing the attention operation inside
a transformer. And so maybe you would
like to you know come up with new
algorithms or new implementations like
flash attention right like what
primitives and what components do we
need to understand in order to be able
to do that right so those are kind of
the two learning goals of today the
first one is you know by the end of the
lecture you should feel kind of
comfortable with GPUs you should kind of
understand how they work and the second
one is you should feel comfortable
accelerating certain parts of your
algorithms you make a new architecture
you should hopefully feel like you can
try to to accelerate that with CUDA Um,
and because hardware is not necessarily
the domain in which I work, you know,
there's uh special resources that I have
to give a lot of credit to, especially
Horus Heath's blog where he's got a lot
of fun GPU facts that you can learn
about. For example, why are matrix
multiplies that are filled with zeros
faster than ones that are not filled
with zeros. You can learn by going to
his blog. There's also other resources
that I've drawn from like the CUDA mode
group and the and the nice TPU book from
Google. Um, if this topic interests you,
you know, I'd encourage you to go and
look at those resources to learn more
because this is in in some ways like a
shallow but hopefully you know complete
coverage of the
hardware. So today we're only going to
focus on uh, you know, nonp parallel
parts of the hardware stack. So we're
going to study the GPU like a single
accelerator in depth, how they work and
some important parts. I'm also going to
talk very very briefly about TPUs
because in some ways they're very
similar conceptually to a GPU. And so my
discussion here is going to carry over.
Um and then once we understand kind of
the hardware and execution model of the
GPU, then we're going to try to
understand what makes GPUs go fast on
certain workloads, what makes them slow.
We're going to understand the
performance. And in the last part, this
is kind of going to be almost like a
hands-on piece. Um I'm going to try to
walk through flash attention, right? I'm
going to take all the lessons that we've
learned and try to walk you through
flash attention saying see here's how it
all comes together. Right? So that's the
last part um of today's
lecture. So you know many of you have
you know taken an NLP course and these
days in an NLP course I think you teach
some amount of scaling laws and so
you've probably seen this right and so
this is just setting the context. Um we
know that having more compute is helpful
for training large language models. Um
this is a pre-training scaling chart but
you could replace this with an inference
scaling chart if you would like. Um it's
generally agreed upon that the more
compute you have the more processing you
can do on your data. You can ingest more
data, you can train larger models, all
of those lead to improved performance,
right? So you might think of, of course,
you know, deep learning is really
important, but what's really driven
performance is, you know, faster
hardware, better utilization, improved
parallelization, right? So that's kind
of setting the stage of why hardware is
important to understand. And of course,
you know, once you think about compute
scaling, you ask, okay, how do we get
compute scaling? How do we get our
models to train faster? So kind of in
the early days you know of of
semiconductor scaling um if you were
thinking about okay are CPUs how do they
get faster um they were they you know
would scale under something called
Dennard scaling right um with Moors law
you would sort of double the the amount
of transistors on a chip every year um
and if you have this doubling what you
end up is um darded scaling where
smaller and smaller transistors can be
driven at faster and faster clock speeds
with lower and lower power um which in
turn give you more performance right and
in the in the 1980s to 2000s, this sort
of tapped out. You can kind of see in
this chart here by Hennessy and
Patterson, that single thread
performance, that's the blue dots here,
um that basically started to taper out.
Of course, the number of transistors
didn't really, you know, start falling
off. You did have, you know, chips with
higher and higher transistor densities,
but that wasn't helpful. It wasn't
giving you higher uh throughput on
single threads. Um and so this means
that we can't just do computation faster
in absolute terms. You know what we have
to make up for it with is parallel
scaling, right? So the story of scaling
for deep learning and neural networks is
going from single thread scaling which
is just doing your computation faster in
absolute terms um to parallel scaling
where you have a lot of workloads that
are all computed at once. Um, and this
is is one of my favorite, you know, uh,
sort of compute scaling charts by by
Bill Dowy in his keynote. Um, where, you
know, he's showing the super exponential
increase in the number of, um, sort of
integer operations per second, um, going
from, you know, the earliest K20s um, to
the H100, right? And it's kind of like
this really remarkable uh, exponential
or super exponential curve. And so, you
know, we have to really understand how
to take advantage of this curve in order
to really get the most out of our
language model, right? So, that's kind
of going to be our
goal. And so, I've already hinted at
this this kind of important difference,
right? CPU is is something that I think
everyone's familiar with once you sort
start doing programming, right? It's
this execution model of you have a
program, it goes through and in a single
thread, it executes step by step what's
happening. And in order to support that
kind of an execution model, what what do
you need? Well, you need big control
units. You just need to generally run
these things very quickly because you
have a lot of branching and you have a
lot of conditional control logic, right?
So a CPU, this is a abstracted diagram
is going to dedicate, you know, a lot of
of its chip towards, you know, large
control branch prediction and it's going
to run these, you know, very quickly
because it doesn't have that many
threads. you know, there there are CPUs
with lots and lots of cores now, but
compared to a GPU, it's almost nothing.
And so in in contrast, the GPU has
really tons and tons of compute units,
ALUS, right? So there's the little green
boxes and there's much smaller amounts
of the chip dedicated to control. So
there's a little bit of control logic
sort of orchestrating tons and tons of
compute units, you know, operating in
parallel. Um, and I think mentally, so
this is kind of the the picture of what
is being emphasized in in a CPU versus
GPU. But if you kind of look at what's
the design goals are, they they designed
for very different sort of goals. So you
can think about CPUs as optimizing for
latency. I want to finish my tasks as
quickly as possible. So if I have tasks
um T1 through uh T4 here on on the right
side, you know, in a CPU, I'm going to
try to finish each task as quickly as
possible. And so if you want any one of
these tasks to be finished quickly, T1's
going to complete really quickly. In
GPU, you're optimizing for high
throughput. Like I don't care about
latency. I just want all of my tasks
that I have in aggregate to complete as
quickly as possible. And to support
that, you know, maybe you have lots of
threads and these threads can go to
sleep and wake up very quickly. Um, and
in the end, you know, you you finish all
of your workload T1 through T4, you
know, before the the CPU one does, even
though individually all of these have
sort of higher latency, right? So they
have different sort of design principles
um and design
goals. Okay. And so um a GPU has a has a
pretty different anatomy. And I don't
know if you know you all have ever
looked at what a a GPU sort of layout
diagram looks like. I'll actually show
you the the chip um figures in a moment
here. Um but the core idea and this is
important conceptual concepts behind a
GPU. um is that a GPU executes you know
uh many many SM streaming
multipprocessors and a streaming
multipprocessor you can kind of think of
as an atomic unit when you're
programming in something like Triton
they're going to operate at the level of
a of an SM and within each SM they're
going to uh it contains many SPS
streaming processors and a streaming
processor is going to execute a whole
bunch of threads in parallel so one way
to think about it is SM has a bunch of
control logic. It can decide what to
execute. It can do, for example,
branching. SPs are going to operate to
to take the same instruction and apply
it to many different pieces of data,
right? And so you can do tons and tons
of parallel computation um under this
model. An SM is sort of each granular
unit of control. SP can do a lot of
computation individually. And if you
look at an A100, which is the previous
generation GPU at this point, um you've
got 128 SM, you know, that's a lot more
than than most cores for for CPUs. And
each of these SM is going to have a very
large number of uh SPS and specialized
sort of matrix multiply units um inside
them. And so that's kind of the the
compute model. Uh was there a question?
Sorry.
Yeah.
to get the slide before GPUs. So is this
GPU the same as a GPU? So the question
was is this GPU the same as that GPU?
Yes. Like this is a this is a kind of
cartoon version of of this. You can kind
of think of each row as being SM. It's
got its own control units. Each green
block might be sort of uh one of these
green blocks here like a SP32 uh sort of
processing unit inside of it. And each
SM can sort of you know operate various
pieces that it that it owns like the
tensor cores to do
computation.
Cool. Okay. And there's going to be uh
two important things. You think of GPU
as you know computers they compute but
actually computation is only one of the
two important things we have to keep
track of right. memory is arguably more
important um at this point and it will
continue to be more important in terms
of the performance profiles of how we
run our programs on the GPU. Um, and so
to understand memory, you kind of have
to understand the physical layout of the
GPU and the chip because in some sense
the, you know, when you're operating at
such fast speeds, the physical proximity
of the memory starts to matter quite a
bit. And so I will show you kind of the
physical proximity of how things are
laid out and how that relates to how you
should think about memory access um, and
performance. So the closer a piece of
memory is to to each SM um, the faster
it's going to be. So there's going to be
certain very very very fast kinds of
memory like L1 um and shared memory and
that's going to live inside uh of the
SM, right? And that's going to be really
fast, right? Things like registers,
things like things you're reading and
writing very frequently, you're going to
want to put into the L1 and shared
memory L2 cache. Um as you can kind of
see, there's these green areas which are
SM. And then there's these blue areas.
This is on the GPU chip, right? These
are L2 uh memory that's sort of right
next to the SM, right? So they're
they're not inside the SM, but they're
physically still quite close, right? Um
and these are still pretty fast. Um you
know, they're they're still a factor of
10 slower, but they're still reasonably
fast. And then outside of the chip
itself, this is sort of a you know, I
think this is like a 3090 card or
something like this or maybe a PCIe 100.
Oh, this is a PCI 100. Um you know,
you've got your your GPU here and you've
got actually DRAM sort of living next to
the chip, right? it has to actually go
physically outside of the chip um and
connect. And you can kind of see on on
this uh chip diagram here, these yellow
connectors at the edges. These are HPM
connectors. Um these are connecting to
the the DRAM chips that are outside of
the actual GPU. And you can kind of see
the the speed that it takes to access
these, right? the onsm memory is much
much faster like 20 clock cycles to
access something from there whereas it's
going to take something like 200 or 300
clock cycles to access something from
the L2 cache or global memory right and
this factor of 10 is going to hurt you
real bad right so if you if you have um
a piece of computation that requires you
to access global memory right it might
mean that you actually run out of work
to do on your SM you've multiplied all
the matrices you've run out now you just
have to idle right so utilization won't
be good and this will be a really key
theme thinking about memories in some
sense the key to thinking about um how
GPUs
work and in assignment two you're going
to you know actually be writing um high
performance code for a GPU so you have
to actually think about um the execution
model of how a GPU actually executes
things um and this is somewhat
complicated but not not insanely so um
the there's sort of three granularities
of things that you need to think about
there's blocks there's warps and there's
threads and that's the order in which
kind of the granularity narrows down,
right? Blocks are kind of these big
groups of threads and each block is
going to be assigned to a SM. So think
about this as each SM is kind of a
worker. It's its own autonomous unit and
a block is going to be assigned to an SM
for to to process, right? So this is
each granular unit. Now then within
these blocks are a whole bunch of
threads. Each thread is a sort of a
piece of task that needs to be done. And
when these threads execute, they're
going to execute in groups. Um, and this
is a thing called a warp, right? So you
take a block, which is a collection of
threads, and you're going to take, you
know, threads from that block, and
they're going to execute in groups of 32
consecutively numbered threads, um, each
time. And that's sort of called, you
know, warps. And so you can kind of see
at this diagram here what's happening.
You've got a bunch of blocks. Each block
is assigned to a different SM. And
within each block, there's going to be
many different warps. And each warp is
going to consist of a whole bunch of
threads and all of these threads are
going to execute um the same instruction
on different data, right? And so this is
kind of the execution model. Right? Now
it's going to it seems probably
mysterious, you know, what these blocks
and warps and threads are. They will
have important implications uh for our
performance in how we design things like
uh CUDA kernels um later. So hopefully
you can kind of remember this. I'll I'll
refresh your memory um kind of as we go.
Um hopefully that's clear.
So that was the kind of logical
execution model of a GPU. Um, and if you
understand that, you kind of understand
how GPUs execute things. Um, there's
also a logical sort of memory model of a
GPU. So, you know, now I'm not showing
you the physical hardware. This is just
kind of how you think about the
programming um, of a GPU. And so there's
registers. So these are really fast, you
know, storing single numbers type
storage. You've got local memory, you
got shared memory, and you've got global
memory, right? And that that increases
in sort of the the memory hierarchy gets
slower and slower and slower. Um and
your code can sort of write to to global
memory. It can also write to constant
memory which is not something that's
that's used too often. Um and so each
thread can access you know its own
register and shared memory. But
information that goes across blocks need
to be written to global memory. This is
actually quite important right. So now
it means that you know whenever you
write a thread that executes something
ideally it's operating on sort of the
same small amount of data. So you load
that small amount of data into shared
memory all the threads are very happy
accessing that shared memory. It
terminates it's done right. That would
be a great execution model. Instead if
you have a thread that needs to access
data all over the place you know that's
going to have to access global memory
that's very very slow. This theme will
come back you know as we talk about
different ways of of operating uh on a
GPU. Um hopefully that's clear. Um
that's kind of the the very you know
high level four slide overview of a GPU.
If you have kind of questions about how
any of that works, feel free to ask me
um as I go
on. Okay, so here's a side thread. Um
last year I didn't cover this because I
think resources on TPU was a little
thin. Um but the nice TPU book or
internet website that I mentioned at the
start of the lecture came out. um and
that has actually a lot of nice details
and I and I talked to a few Google
people about the TPU um and at a high
level it's very very similar um to a GPU
and so I want to just talk for a moment
about TPUs you may never you know
operate on a TPU but I think it's
important to understand that these
alternative accelerators operate in in
in many ways very similarly
um so here's a diagram of what a TPU
looks like um there's kind of a so
there's something called a tensor core
and mentally you can think about a
tensor core as being similar to SM or
streaming multipprocessor. Each of these
are are kind of its own atomic units
that can operate on data. There's a
scalar unit which is basically a control
unit and it can also do CPU like
arbitrary things. You've got a vector
unit that can operate on vectors. So if
you got a vector and you want to operate
entry-wise on it, that's a good place to
do it. And then it's got a very big
specialized, you know, part of the chip
dedicated to just doing matrix
multiplies called the MXU. Um, and then
it's got very fast memory for vector
memory and SME. Both of these are very
fast onchip or like on tensor core
memory and then there's high bandwidth
memory that lives outside of the chip.
Right? So hopefully you see the
similarities to an SM, right? There's
slow memory outside, very fast memory
inside and there's specialized hardware
to do matrix multiplication. Core
structure is very much the same. Um the
difference is um I'll talk about this in
the parallelism lecture next week. You
know how the accelerators are together
is a little bit different. Um and then
also you know mention I didn't notice I
didn't talk about warps. I didn't talk
about any of that other stuff. Um,
tensor cores are in some ways very
simple because they're optimized to just
do matrix multiplies, right? Like the
tensor core unlike the GPU doesn't
attempt to do anything but that. And so
that's in some ways very very simple. Uh
much simpler in architecture but
conceptually doing the same thing.
Yes.
Is it tensor also in some ways optimized
to general tensor or this is just enough
to work on?
Yeah. So, so the question was you know
is it called tensor because it can
operate on arbitrary tensors. Um so it
can operate on arbitrary tensors like
can do the indexing the operations that
MXU performs is a matrix multiply and so
it would always be like a batch matrix
multiply operating on a tensor. So it's
kind of both a yes and a no answer if
that makes sense. So they operate on
tensors but the operations they always
perform are matrix multiplies not more
complicated tensor operations that you
can
do. Cool. Um the reason why the GPU has
been so successful is that you know it
scales up really easily. If you want
more processing power just add more SMS
right you don't have to worry about
driving the clock faster and getting
more heat dissipation problems. Um
programming wise um CUDA is intimidating
but it's actually you know not as
horrendous to program because of the its
programming model like the way it works
is within each SM right you have a
thread and it executes the same
instruction on a bunch of different
pieces of data right that's conceptually
sort of easy to reason about you can
think through what that means and
especially it's nice if you're operating
over a matrix and you're doing sort of
very simple operations it's exactly this
kind of simp model um finally each of
these threads are very lightweight and
they can be kind of stopped and started
at any time. And so if you need to wait
for another thread um or if you need to
sort of like evict something and like
start another process, all these threads
are very lightweight. So this just kind
of means that there's not much state
associated with the threads and they can
kind of be stopped and started which
allows GPUs to get high utilization um
within sort of each
SM. So GPUs, you know, obviously
graphics processing units. Um, and for
for much of its life, you know, in the
early days, it was not used to do
scientific computing. Um, but you know,
people because it was programmable,
researchers figured out how to use, you
know, early NVIDIA GPUs to do fast
matrix multiplies. Um, this is one of
the early papers on, you know, doing
fast matrix multiplies with graphics
hardware. Um, and it shows, you know,
how you can, you know, hack kind of
things like the texture buffer and so
on, uh, to get it to do matrix
multiplies, right? And so you know even
without specific support for mapm you
know researchers figured out how to do
it but I think now you know especially
in this day and age nvidia and others
have realized matrix multiplies are
special like if you're doing deep
learning right most of your workload is
matrix multiplies and so matrix
multiplies are in some sense blessed
operations so this is um a chart showing
um the number of teraflops per second by
different generations of Nvidia GPUs and
the orange line is your map mo flops
right? Like with your performance you
can get if you're doing matt moles. The
blue line is your non-matmo flops,
right? And you see kind of this big big
gap at v 100's when um they started
putting in sort of tensor cores that
were specialized hardware to do matrix
multiplies. And you see this gigantic
gap uh in the matrix multiply
performance relative to the non-mappable
performance, right? Um, and so if you're
going to design any sort of a neural
architecture, I was saying this, you
know, in the architecture part as well,
you have to have most of your workload
be matrix multiplies because that's the
thing that's, you know, orders of
magnitude faster than any other
operation that you're going to be able
to do uh on a GPU, right? So if you make
like a non-natmo based neural network,
you're going to be in a big big trouble.
And then kind of the the last thing that
I want you to kind of understand as just
general facts. Um you know matt moles is
fast is one thing but the other thing
that's important to remember is kind of
the relative scaling of the different
components of the GPU. So this is a very
nice chart that shows you know how
quickly different components of the uh
GPU or different components of the let's
call it like LM training stack are
scaling. So the blue line is the
connectivity from the GPU to the host,
right? Like the the server that it's
attached to, right? So you you can use
PCIe, you can use NVLink, you can use
all these these fancy interconnects.
They are growing, but they're growing
somewhat slowly, right? So so this chart
is like normalized scaling, you know,
bandwidth relative to to when you know
the the first generation um of
interconnects. The green line, this is
the uh global memory speed, right? So
you go from GDDR to HBM2E and that's
much much faster right this is log scale
it's 100x faster um but this is still
kind of slow scaling right and the gray
line here right this is compute scaling
this is the number of floatingoint
operations if you're you know
considering the map flops this is this
is how fast the compute has been scaling
and this is astoundingly fast it's like
one to 100,000 times faster um and so
kind of in the early days of the scaling
maybe your problems were flops based
right like you you just didn't have
enough flops to do your matrix
multiplications. But now, you know, all
the way to the right with the H100's,
you know, these are astoundingly fast
GPUs, your bottlenecks are probably
going to end up being memory, right?
Because the memory is not growing as
fast, right? And as we go into the
future, you know, this is not really
going to change. DRAM is very hard to
scale. You're going to keep getting this
bigger and bigger gap, right? So, if
you're ever designing, you know,
hardware efficient algorithms, you're
going to have to think more and more
about memory, right? And so, we're going
to keep a lookout on that. I'm going to
keep emphasizing this. It's one of the
important themes um in GPUs. Okay, so
you know I've been kind of throwing lots
of GPU facts at you um especially if you
haven't you know seen this recently and
maybe kind of new. So just to recap,
right, GPUs are these massively parallel
processing systems. They have same
instructions applied across many
different threads and they have these
things called SM which are kind of like
cores that you know there's many many of
them in the GPUs. um compute and and
matrix multiplies have scaled really
fast and they have scaled faster than
memory and that is an important part of
the characteristics that you think about
about GPUs but there is some fast memory
right it's not like everything is slow
so there's nothing we can do there's the
memory hierarchy right so some kinds of
memory are very very fast other kinds of
memories are slow and so if we exploit
this hierarchy maybe we can get things
that are really really fast right so
that's kind of things to remember about
the GPU and if you remember these facts
you know you're going to be able think
pretty cleanly about the performance
components that I'm going to talk about
next. Um, any questions before I I move
on to the next
part. Okay,
cool. So now you all are GPU experts and
what we would like to do is we would
like to make machine learning workloads
go very fast on a GPU. Um, and so I'm
going to start with this chart and one
of our goals will be to understand what
this chart exactly is. I think it'll be
a good puzzle to get us motivated. Um,
and so here what we are doing is we are
multiplying square matrices together,
right? So the x-axis is the size of my
square matrix multiplies. And you know
the y-axis here, this is the number of
operations per second that I'm doing. So
you can kind of think of this as
hardware utilization on the y ais,
right? Um, and so as I get bigger and
bigger matrices, I'm going to get better
and better hardware utilization because,
you know, I I have more work to do. So I
don't you know that overwhelms the
overhead of sort of you know launching
jobs and things like this. Um, but
there's all these weird things that are
happening, right? You see one, two,
three different, four different lines,
right? And each of these lines are kind
of wavy in a way that's kind of, you
know, looks very unpredictable, right?
Um, and so we would like to kind of
understand what exactly is going on uh
with these lines. And by the end of this
section, um, my promise is that you will
kind of understand exactly each one of
these phenomenon. You'll be able to say,
"Yeah, that plot looks totally normal.
That is a natural thing for a GPU to
do."
Okay, so the very first part, right, is
if you look at that plot, you will
notice that it looks a little bit like
this, right? And if you've taken a
systems hardware course, you know, you
should you should remember this as kind
of the roof line model. Um the roofline
model basically says if we're looking
at, you know, throughput or utilization,
um you know, what we're going to find
is, you know, there's two regimes.
There's going to be a regime that is
sort of memory limited, right? That is
on the left side of this curve on the
green over here. And then there's a part
that is throughput limited on the right
side. In some sense you can kind of
think of it as on the right side we have
we are fully utilizing our compute
units. All the matrix multiply units are
multiplying all the time. Um and on the
diagonal here we just have some sort of
memory bottleneck and so our ability to
to do computation is limited by kind of
the amount of sort of intensity that we
have the amount of flops per bite that
we have. Right? So we want to avoid
being in this left side region where
we're memory bound and we would like to
be on this right side where we're
getting in some sense full utilization
of all of our compute units. Right? So
that's in some sense the goal and
hopefully this roofine model looks
something like this. Right? Like we've
got sort of this diagonal part and then
we've got this flat part all the way at
the top here. So that's one part of the
mystery. Um and so this is this turns
out to be kind of complex, right? Um,
the simple way to say this is let's make
sure that we're not accessing memory
unnecessarily, right? We have as few
memory accesses to slow global memory as
possible. But it turns out that in order
to do that, we need a large array of
tricks. Um, there's a lot of different
things that you could do that would mess
you up, that would make you very slow.
And the first one's not a memory
bottleneck. I'll just mention it. Um, it
doesn't come up too often. we'll get it
out of the way and then we'll talk about
the remaining uh five items that in some
sense are really core to thinking about
GPU
performance. Okay, so the first thing
that I want to talk about is
conditionals. Um so as I said before
GPUs their execution model is something
called SIM key right single instruction
multi-thread. Um and so every thread in
a warp is going to execute the same
instruction um and it's going to do so
on different data. And so what happens
if I write uh a piece of code that looks
like this? I have an if statement and if
you know the thread index is less than
four do something. If the thread index
is greater than or equal to four then do
something else. Right? I have this very
simple conditional uh model. If I run
this on the GPU um what's going to
happen is that I'm going to run the a uh
instruction on four of my threads. I
will actually pause my other four
threads which are supposed to be
executing the else part. And then these
other four threads will come live and
they will execute X and these my
original four threads will will go to
sleep and I will just alternate
executing each of these instructions.
Why is that? I can't in I can't execute
A and X at the same time on these
different threads. Right? As I said
again um every thread has to execute the
same instruction. So conditional
statements within a single warp um can
be really really damaging because they
will force you to pause any of the
threads that are not doing exactly the
the main sort of control flow uh
execution. Okay, so that was the the
only non-memory thing that I wanted to
mention. Um and it should be kind of
obvious that you should probably not be
putting conditionals um into sort of
your uh massively parallel compute unit.
But once we've gotten that out of the
way, sort of the other tricks that we
need to consider are all kind of memory
based. Um the first thing I want to sort
of mention is lower precision. And this
is a big trick. This is an important
trick. You should do it all the time. Um
there's kind of a going back to this
plot um of of Billy. Um there's a slight
of hand here. Um this looks really good
because the the numbers are going up and
up and up. But if you look at, you know,
what's driving GPU progress over all
these years, um, you actually kind of
see that it's number representations.
You go from FP32 to FP16 to intate to to
so on, uh, you get many orders of
magnitude gains from just having lower
and lower precision in your GPU
operations. Um, and let me let me sort
of clarify why that's so important,
right? If you have fewer bits in all the
things that you're computing and your
weights and so on, you have much fewer
bits to move, right? So even if you're
accessing these bits from global memory,
um they become much much less of a
concern. So let's just give a simple
example and let's just think about kind
of arithmetic intensity of a simple
element-wise operation. Right? So I'm
going to do it in values. So that's x
equals max zero and x and I'm going to
do that on a vector of size n. Let's say
naively I'm going to do this on float
32. Right? So so how many memory
accesses do I have? I have to read my x.
I have to write the result of if x less
than zero. Um and that's all in float
32. So that's kind of eight bytes,
right? And how many operations do I do?
Well, I have to do x less than zero. So
that's one comparison operation. And I
do one flop, right? So so I do, you
know, eight bytes per single
floatingoint operation. If I do this in
float 16 now, well, you know, I haven't
changed the flops intensity here, but
I've have the memory access. And so now
I have four bytes per flop, right? In
some sense, I've like gotten double the
memory bandwidth for free, assuming that
I can get away with flop 16.
And this is a key part of of how a lot
of things are designed. Part of the
assignment is going to be you're going
to, you know, try and and play with uh
various like mixed precision or low
precision uh training and and other
kinds of things. Um and a key part here
is that not all the parts of your
network and your training algorithm
should be put into low precision, right?
So let me give you an example of matrix
multiplies. So in matrix multiplies that
are mixed precision what you would do is
you would have you know your inputs be
16 bit. So these are low precision. Um
and then you're going to do your your
multiplication in full 32bit right and
that's useful because the intermediate
computations as you're like accumulating
partial sums you would like that to be
in high precision. Um and so you're
accumulating this with uh FP32
accumulator and then you know your
tensor core uh will return a FP32 result
um which you can you know downcast if
you would like um back into into 16 bit
right and so we have our inputs in 16
bit but things like the accumulation um
we might want to do in 32 right so
there's lots of different things there's
operations that can use 16- bit storage
there's operations that might need more
precision so you want to keep it in like
either FP32 or FP16. Um, think you might
want to have operations that need more
range like X functions. If you don't
have sort of the dynamic range, they
might blow up or zero out. And so you
might want to put those in BF-16.
There's a lot of sort of careful
engineering um that has to happen in
order to make sure that you know these
these models uh are actually stable when
they're being trained with lower
precision. But if you can do it, that's
really great because you've basically
doubled the throughput of your
bottleneck going from 32 to 16 bit,
right? if your if your memory is your
bottleneck. Okay, the other one and I
think this is kind of what a lot of
people think of when they say like I'm
going to write a CUDA kernel or
something. Um, operator fusion is kind
of both very intuitive and both a like a
fun natural one to think about. So, one
memory or sorry, one mental model of how
a GPU works and how memory works is is
this kind of fun diagram of a factory um
from Horus Heath, right? So imagine you
have a factory and your factory is your
compute part, right? And so you know it
takes in little uh box widgets and then
outputs little triangle widgets. Um and
if you grow your compute but your belt
conveyor, you know that takes memory to
compute is, you know, finite bandwidth,
you know, you're not going to be able to
use your second factory, right? Like
you're still capped by the speed at
which you can transfer things um from
memory to compute. And so you've got
this this bottleneck. Now, of course,
you already knew that, right? I've been
sort of hammering in the the memory
bottleneck thing. But I think one
insidious way in which you can uh incur
a ton of overhead without really
realizing it is kind of this left-hand
side computation pattern, right? So, you
know, imagine the left side of this this
plot is where the memory is. The right
side is your compute unit. Um and so to
do computation, I start with a square
and I move my squares from my memory to
my compute. I do some operation. I turn
them into triangles. Right? Now, I ship
my triangles back to memory. And then
you know, okay, I realize I need a
triangles again. So I ship them back
into the compute unit. Now the triangles
become circles and then so on and so
forth, right? I send my compute sort of
back and forth and back and forth back
to memory. And you might call this kind
of a very naive approach. And if you
were just doing operations naively on
the GPU and just shipping the results
straight back to global memory, this is
what you'd end up with, right? And if
you count the number of times a piece of
data went back and forth, this is this
is pretty terrible. You've incurred tons
of memory overhead. Now uh you should be
able to realize that if you look at the
right side well this compute well
there's no dependency so I should be
able to go square to triangle to circle
to to rectangle and ship the rectangle
back right I can just keep everything in
the compute unit the whole time right
and that's the right hand side diagram
and this is the mental model of a fused
kernel right you have a bunch of
operations that are going to happen on a
piece of data in sequence instead of
writing it back into storage what I'm
going to do is I'm going to do all the
computation as much as I can in one
place and then only when I have to ship
it back to memory. Right? So that's this
idea of of kernel
fusion. Okay. Um there's some very
simple examples of how if you write some
naive code um you might you know get
sort of a naive set of launches. So
here's an example. Um I wrote a little
let's say neural network module. um you
know let's say let's say I write a
neural network module that takes in uh s
x and it produces sin^ squar x and
cosine^ squ x right simple code now if I
run this you know the computation graph
in pietorch is going to look something
like this and it's going to you know
launch a whole bunch of cuda kernels
it's going to launch take in the x and
it'll it'll launch a cuda kernel to
compute sin x it'll launch one to
compute cosine x then sin square of x
and cosine square of x and sin^ square x
plus cosine square of x right so there's
a bunch of back and forth that has to
happen in order to do this computation.
It's exactly the lefth hand side figure
uh that I showed you
before. Um but if you were a little
smarter, right, and you either wrote
your own CUDA kernel or you use
something like torch compile, um well,
you can easily realize that those five
operations um don't really depend on
very much like they they use only a
little bit of memory. And so you can
fuse them into a single operation that
does everything on GPU on a single
thread without sending things back to
global memory. Right? So um really easy
fusion operations like this can be done
automatically by compilers. I just
mentioned torch compile. Um if you
aren't already doing this, you know, you
should you should consider strongly
thinking about using torch compile
everywhere. Um we'll show you in the
assignment um torch compile as well.
It's it's pretty uh nice. Okay. Um, so
I've gone through uh precision and
fusion. If anyone has questions, let me
know uh before I move on to to
recomputation um and other kinds of
tricks that we can do on the
GPU. Okay,
good. So another thing that we can do is
called recomputation. Um and
recomputation is this idea of sort of
spending more compute to uh avoid having
to do memory access, right? Um, so
remember back your, you know, original
back propagation lecture. This one's
actually from CS221. Um, what do we do?
Well, we take our our inputs at the very
bottom. These are the yellow ones. Um,
and then we propagate activations
upwards. Those are also the yellow
values on the on the tree. Um, and then
we compute the Jacobians backwards.
Those are the green values on the edges.
And then to compute my gradients, I'm
going to propagate you multiply sort of
the Jacobian and the activations. I'm
going to propagate the the gradients
backward, right? Um, well, if you think
about it, those yellow values after the
forward pass have to be stored, right?
And then they're stored and then they
have to be taken from global memory
where I stored them and put them into
the compute units, right? Mechanically,
that's how it has to happen. Um, but
that might actually be a ton of sort of
memory inputs and outputs
happening. Instead, you might actually
be able to avoid this. So, let me give
you an example of how recomputation can
speed things up. Um, here's another sort
of silly uh function that I might write.
I'm just going to stack three sigmoids
on top of each other, right? You can
look at the left. That's the forward
graph. Um, that should be exactly, you
know, your mental model of three
sigmoids on top of each other. Now, you
know, the the computation graph for
this, I'm going to compute the sigmoids
and I'm going to store S1 and S2, which
are the activations of the sigmoids, and
I have my outputs. Um, and then, you
know, that's my sort of forward pass.
Now, the backward pass in this is kind
of terrible. when I do my backward
graph, I need to go and take S1 and S2
um and I need to take you know the the
gradients coming sort of backwards into
this out box um and then push it into
this you know backwards computation and
I'll get the gradient of X right so I
need to have three memory reads one
memory right in order to compute the
backwards pass and then for the forward
pass I need to do one memory read of X
and I need to do three memory rights for
S1 S2 and out right so hopefully that's
clear this is you know a decent amount
of of uh memory reads and writes have to
do eight of them and I have very low
arithmetic intensity because I have no
matrix multiplies um at
all. So the idea of recomputation is to
say I don't want to store those
activations at all. Right? Like I'm not
going to put them into memory. I'm just
going to recmp compute them on the fly
in my backward pass. Right? So now in my
new forward pass I don't store S1 and
S2. I take X as input. I compute my
sigmoids and I get my output. Right? So
now that's one memory read for X, one
memory right for out. Right? Um, now in
my backward pass, right, I don't have
activations anymore. So what I'm going
to do is I'm going to get both D out,
which is, you know, the backward signal
coming in from above. Um, and then X,
which is my input, right? So I'm going
to take two of those, which is two
memory reads. Um, and then sort of on
the fly in my SM in my local memory, I'm
going to compute each of these sigmoids,
and I'm going to put them into the
backward graph, right? I'm going to
recmp compute S1, S2, uh, and out on the
fly inside sort of my local memory. Um
and because I do that there's no global
memory reads happening here. Um and then
I have one memory right which is dx.
Right? So now if you compare the two um
I have 5/8 of the memory access for the
exact same computation. Right? The price
that we paid is that I'm going to have
to recomputee these three sigmoids. But
if you were running sort of idle anyway
because you were memory capped, this is
a a great trade-off, right? Like you
would be very happy with this because
now you've traded compute which you have
too much of for memory bandwidth which
you had too little of. Right? Right. So
this is one great way of trading um one
thing you need for another thing uh that
you
have. And of course this is different uh
it's the same trick as um sort of
gradient checkpointing and recmp
computing activations for memory
savings. Um but this is being done for
different reasons. This is for uh sort
of execution speed not just because
you're running out of memory. Right? So
it's it's the same technique but for
different
goals. Okay. And then this one I think
um is actually kind of a really
interesting one and and not one that I
knew until I started sort of really
looking into how the hardware model of a
GPU uh and DRAM works. Um,
so the slow memory, the global memory
called DRAM in a GPU, um, that's
actually very very slow. And in order to
to make it faster, there's certain
optimizations that are being done at the
hardware level. And one of the
optimizations that's done at a hardware
level for for DRAM is that when you go
and read a piece of memory, you don't
actually get just that value back. You
actually get a whole chunk of the memory
back. Um, and this is called burst mode.
So um let's say I went on and uh tried
to read the very first value of this big
memory block, right? Instead of just the
memory giving me back zero, it would
actually give me back 012 3, right? It
would give me back four values at once.
It'll be like here you go. You know, I'm
sure you'll need the one, two, and three
too in the future. Um and so each
address space is cut up into what's
called burst sections. And then you're
given the entire burst section rather
than just what you looked for.
And this might seem very mystifying like
why would the memory give you three
extra, you know, bytes for free uh when
you're just asking for one. Um there's
sort of like a very interesting hardware
reason which is that when you're
addressing into the memory, you know, in
order to send the signal out from the
memory that those bytes have to be moved
to an amplifier. That's the slow step.
And once you've done that, you can get
many many bytes for free. And so that's
why sort of this burst section thing
exists. it's kind of masking this more
expensive step of actually moving where
the the data is stored to this
amplifier but kind of regardless um this
kind of means that we might be able to
significantly accelerate sort of our
memory access if the pattern of memory
access is good right so if I want to
read um this entire you know block over
here if I access it in random order
right then I'm going to have to you know
basically query uh a number of times
equal roughly to the length of my query.
Right? But if I sort of go and I check
the very first value, then I'm going to
get all this entire burst section at
once. And then if I go and check number
four, I'll get this burst section, the
second burst section at once. And so I
can, you know, uh, basically get four
times the throughput if I'm really
clever about my memory accesses and only
access just the bits I need from each
uh, burst section. So this is called
memory coallesing. So if all the threads
uh in in a warp fall within the same
burst um then basically the sort of
smart hardware and programming model
will basically group those queries.
instead of querying 0 1 2 3 it will
group them and say just give me zero and
then I will be able to read out all the
0 1 2 3 at once from this kind of burst
mode uh DRAM right so remember that you
know a warp is 32 sort of numbered
threads and so memory accesses from a
warp happen together and so when these
warps are reading in to these kind of
burst sections there's optimizations
that can be done so that you're getting
all four bytes at once rather than
getting one of them at a time
individually and so that will 4x uh the
throughput that you have on your memory.
Right? So these are kind of very simple
things, but they're actually very
important. Like imagine I'm going to do
matrix multiplications, right? This is a
core thing that you're going to have to
do a ton if you were to sort of
implement, let's say, uh neural network
really from scratch in CUDA. Um in this
case, imagine I'm going to read my my uh
matrices in one of two ways. I can read
it by traversing the rows, right? So
each thread is going to traverse the
row. Or I can sort of read it in sort of
column order. So each thread is going to
go down a column, right? Um turns out
that this left one where you're sort of
going across different rows, so each
thread is accessing a different Oh,
sorry, each thread is going through
columns. This left model is going to be
quite slow. Um because the memory reads
are not going to be coalesed. Um whereas
if you're going to this right side where
each of the threads are going down, so
they're they're incrementing in rows,
then these memory reads will be
coalesed. Um and so you know you can
think about it for a moment why this is
true. Um when I first looked at this
diagram I was like isn't it reversed?
It's actually not. This is this is the
correct one. Um and the way to think
about this right um is let's say uh on
this right hand side diagram over here.
I'm going to have a thread that's trying
to a series of threads that's trying to
access you know left to right. So each
thread is going to try to load you know
the very first element and then in the
next time step I'm going to the load the
element from the uh this column the
second column and then the third column
and the fourth column and so on. So if
that happens, what happens at time step
one? Right? At time step one, my first
thread loads this point and then the
second thread loads this point and then
this point and that point, right? So
those can't be coalesed at all. They're
reading different burst sections. And so
that means that I have to read this
entire chunk of memory in order to
perform any sort of an operation.
Instead, if I was sort of going in the
column direction, all the threads will
be reading within the single burst
section. And then so only one memory
read operation needs to be performed and
you get all the memory at once. Right?
This is a very low-level optimization,
but this is very important. Right? If
your memory traversal order is all
wrong, you you will actually get much
slower memory accesses than you really
want.
Okay? So then uh that brings us to kind
of the very last and kind of big one. Um
and this is the idea of uh tiling. Um
and tiling is this idea that you would
like to group together memory accesses
um in order to minimize the amount of
global memory access that we have to do.
And so to explain this one uh I'm going
to try to go through this example of a
matrix multiply. And hopefully I'll be
able to sort of explain to you um why
sort of a naive algorithm for doing
matrix multiply is going to be very
problematic. And then afterwards I'm
going to give you a tiled version of the
same idea. And hopefully you'll be able
to see why that's going to reduce the
number of global memory reads um that
you have to do. So let's start with this
very simple matrix multiply uh
algorithm. So you know I've got a matrix
you know I got this M matrix on the left
side. I've got my N matrix on the top.
Um, and in order to compute, you know,
the matrix matrix product, right, I'm
going to have to traverse over the rows
of M and the columns of N and then take
the inner product and store that into uh
this P matrix, right, the corresponding
rows. Um, and I've written out here um
each of the threads, the thread 01 1 0 1
corresponding to where they're sort of
storing their outputs and sort of the
access order in which they access each
of the individual elements. Now notice
here that you know what's going to
happen is that the memory access here is
not coalesed like the row um uh matrices
here these are going to be accessed in a
non-co order and I have repeated memory
accesses right so I've got m00 0 being
accessed in the first thread m 0
accessed here n0 n10 being accessed in
two different threads you know so these
values are being kind of read um over
and over from global memory into many
different threads
And so this is going to be potentially
very slow. So there's a question of can
we avoid having too many global memory
reads and writes. What I would ideally
like to do, right? So let me explain
kind of the the ideal outcome first and
then I'll explain the algorithm. The
ideal outcome is that I would like to
spend one sort of, you know, chunk of
time loading pieces from global memory
to shared memory where things are fast.
I want to do a ton of computation in
shared memory and then I want to kind of
be done with that piece of uh data.
Right? That's the ideal outcome. I've
minimized my global memory accesses. So
now how can I do this um in this matrix
multiply world? So now what I'm going to
do is I'm going to take my matrices both
the M matrix and the N matrix and I'm
going to cut them up right into tiles.
So here I've cut this up into 2x2 tiles.
So I've got a 2x2 M tile and a 2x2 N
tile right. So I've got basically uh
smaller submatrices within each of the
matrix. And now imagine that my shared
memory is big enough to be able to fit
these submatrices, right? Uh within each
of these SM. So now this gives a very
very simple uh algorithm with which we
can do computation. So uh what I'm going
to do is I'm going to first load you
know let's say this m00 tile on the top
left over here and I'm going to also
load my N00 tile um into shared memory
here. Right? Um, so now I have these
partial sums that I can compute. I can
take, you know, the the row product of
m00 z m01 with n z n 0 and I can
increment that into p 0. I can do the
same with all the different submatrices
that I can fill out over here. Right now
then once I'm completely done sort of
processing these two tiles, then I can
load a new tile over here. And then I
can repeat that computation with my M
tile and my N2.0 tile loaded into shared
memory. And then I can sort of increment
my partial sums in P. Right? So now I've
really sort of consolidated and reduced
the amount of global memory access I
have to do. Right? I I load as much
memory as I can at once into shared
memory. I do all of my sort of submatrix
computations on that tile that I can and
then I move on to the next one. Right?
Um and of course the other nice thing is
that because I'm loading um an entire
tile, you know, I can traverse these
submatrices matrices in whatever order I
want like column measure or row measure.
And so I can coales all the memory
accesses whenever I'm loading a tile
from global to shared memory. Right? So
so there's kind of winds all around here
um when we tile our
accesses. So we can do a little bit of
of tiling math. Um so we've got let's
say a matrix A, a matrix B, and a matrix
C. So let's say the full matrices these
are square matrices are of size N. And
let's say I have a tile of size T,
right? Oh yes, question. Previous slide
of
load m0. So three loading m00 0 again.
So in that case I just wrote it for for
completeness but m00 z let's say is just
you know stored in shared memory. Let's
just keep it cached. I won't load it
again. That that's definitely just there
for completeness. Not that you would
actually like discard and reload the the
uh matrix again. That would be kind of
insane. Cool. Okay. Um, and so we can
kind of do very simple tiling math to
think about, you know, what's happening.
So let's say I'm going to do a n byn
matrix multiply, right? Um, so if I do a
non-tiled matrix multiply, if I'm just
going over rows and columns, then every
input every time I process it has to
come from global memory. So each input
is read sort of n times from global
memory, right? So each of these is read
sort of n times. Um, if I do a tiled
matrix multiply, well, you know, the the
global reads are operating over a tile.
So I'm reading each input n over t times
from global memory and I'm reading t
times within each tile right of course
I'm doing matrix matrix multiplies so I
can't reduce the total number of reads I
have to read all the matrix elements but
I can shift the reads into uh basically
fast shared memory right so I do t times
um memory reads into shared memory and n
overt times from global memory um and
that's great because if we have a big
shared memory that can store big tiles
that's a factor of t reduction in the
total amount of data that has to come
from global memory. Right? So tiling can
be really really powerful um of an idea
when you're operating over matrices and
you can move things um into shared
memory. Um tiling is is quite complex.
Um this is the source of many many sort
of uh confusing things about GPU and
matrix multiply performance. Um one
thing that can happen right once we
start tiling things you start asking
things about discretization right. Um,
so imagine I have a tile size of 128.
That seems like a nice good round tile
size. Um, but then um, you know, when I
have a a full matrix of 256 size, that's
great. That's a 2x2 tile. Things load
nicely. Now, let's say I have a 257 size
tile, um, on the column side. Now, this
is a bad time because I need to have six
tiles in order to cover this matrix. And
the two tiles on the right are very,
very sparse. there's just not much stuff
in there, right? And the problem with
this is that each tile is going to be
assigned to SM, right? So each of these
tiles is going to be a block and each
thread is going to be operating within
each tile. So those two tiles on the
right, they're not going to be doing
very much at all, right? Those SM are
going to be basically be sitting idle.
Um, and if you were kind of compute
capped, you would have wanted to more
evenly distribute the load uh between
SM, right? So um you have to basically
optimize your tile sizes to try to avoid
these kinds of scenarios. But in
reality, right, there's a lot of complex
things that go into setting the tile
size, right? Um remember you have to
coales your memory accesses. So you have
to think carefully about that. You have
to um uh m you have to not exceed your
shared memory size, right? So so the
tiles can't be too big. And you have to
divide the matrix dimension hopefully
evenly or as close to evenly as possible
so you don't end up with this situation
of sort of an underutilized SM um at the
very end
here. Um yes so you have say smaller
sizes do something like would GPUs do
something like where they can like fetch
the tile beforehand and if so like would
that happen the level? Yeah. So you're
you're asking about whether or not you
can like overlap uh memory reads and
computation and yeah that's that's
naturally done in uh GPUs like they're
always like trying to use the the
available bandwidth. Like as long as
shared memory is available they can go
and put things into it. The issue is
that whenever you're you know
effectively utilizing um your SMS you're
basically maxed out on your shared
memory right that's like the the the
bottlenecked resource and so there is no
place to prefetch in some sense.
Cool. Okay.
Um, and the other thing that is very
very, you know, we're getting into the
weeds here, um, complex is the
interaction between tiling, um, and sort
of burst sections. Um, so imagine I have
a a matrix layout that's kind of like
this. Um, where, you know, I have my
nice burst sections. Um, and each burst
section lines up nicely with a tile. So
to read this tile, all I have to do is
to, you know, get four different burst
sections and I've gotten this entire
tile. Now imagine what happens if I add
sort of one element extra and the way
the the matrix is laid out, you know, my
sort of tile start sort of my burst
sections flow over. So now what's
happening is when I load my tile, I'm
going to load this first part and that's
really great. I get the entire first row
as a burst section. Now in the second
row, this actually belongs to two
different burst sections. And so I have
to do two reads in order to get this
second row and so on and so forth. So
I've essentially doubled the number of
memory accesses because I've added a
single extra element at the very end
there that's kind of bumped up the
alignment of my burst section and my
align layout. And so basically if tiles
or your matrix sizes aren't multiples of
your burst section, you can easily end
up with situations like this where the
rows don't line up with the burst
section and you've doubled the amount of
memory access that you have to do. Um,
and the way to get around this is you
have to do padding to be able to kind of
get nice round matrix sizes so that your
burst sections line up with the size of
your tiles. Right? So this is this is
getting very into the weeds here. Um but
if you really want to squeeze out all
the performance from your matrix
multiplies, these are the kinds of
things you have to think about, right?
And you will get bitten by this um if
you're not thinking about it.
Um and of course, I guess like uh things
like torch compile and and all the CUDA
optimizations for matrix multiplies,
they're doing exactly the kinds of stuff
that that I just talked about, right?
That's the way you you get better
performance. Um and so you know all this
matrix complexity you know ends up in
situations like this um where you know
the I'm reading Andre's this tweet here
but you know the the most dramatic
optimization to nano GPT is to increase
the vocab size from 5257 to 5304
um which is the nearest multiple 64 um
which gives you much much higher
occupancy um careful with your powers of
two right so that's a 25% speed up from
adding uh how many it's like 50 uh 57 no
47 uh dimensions to your vocap like
that's that's kind of like you know how
does that happen right um and so that
kind of brings us back to the mystery
like you know I I was dragging you
through all the GPU details um in the
hopes that you know you'll have a full
understanding of all the performance
characteristics but in some sense the
payoff is you know I now get to explain
to you how this chart comes to be and at
the end you won't find matrix multiply
performance to be so uh mysterious or
scary um at the end here, right? So the
very first part is very very simple like
we understand compute intensity, right?
This is exactly the roof line that I
pointed out at the very beginning,
right? So so up until here, which is
about 1536, right? Um there's just not
enough matrix multiply work to do,
right? The just loading the matrix and
doing very basic IO, right, that you
have to do is becoming a bottleneck
below this point, right? So throughput
is going to fall through to the ground.
uh uh past this point you just don't
have enough memory bandwidth to support
your compute units. Now on the right
side here in theory right if you if I
draw the upper envelope this is the kind
of maximum achievable performance. So
it's possible up here to saturate all of
my compute units and get really great
performance. But if you kind of mess up
your matrix sizing you can end up in
these kind of really weird places and
within each one of these you can kind of
end up in a weird trough. And so we're
going to kind of think a little bit
about you know why do you have all these
different places you can end
up. Um so the very first thing um this
first line here um this is a a tiling
alignment issue. So if you look at um
kind of the multiples here so I've now
colored each of these lines based on
kind of the divisibility of the matrix
size um and this is the size by which
it's divisible. So if it's divisible by
32 then you're in good shape. you're in
these purple dots up here. If you're
divisible by uh 16, um you're actually
uh still up here. There's two colors.
And then if you're green, your k equals
8, you're up here. If you're orange,
you're k equals 2. And if you're k
equals 1, you're all the way down here.
If you're not divisible by any number,
uh don't pick prime dimensions. You're
not going to get very good throughput on
your matrix multiplies. Um, and a big
part of this is going to be, you know,
once you get to kind of k equals 2 and k
equals 1, you are basically forcing the
situation where you can no longer read
tiles in the sort of nicely aligned way
with your burst reads. And that's going
to lead to to some serious issues. So,
so that's kind of a
problem. But then, okay. So, so that's
one part of the mystery, but I think
another part of the mystery remains.
Like, so within this orange line, you
know, I think if you zoom into here, you
see this giant drop, right, from from
this point all the way down to this
point where you're just kind of
wondering what happened here? How could
I lose so much performance increasing my
dimension by
two? Um, and so let's just look at these
numbers. Um, and it's just I think this
is a fun puzzle. So, I'm just going to
walk you through the puzzle. Um this is
going to happen when you transition from
1792 to 1790 uh I guess three or four um
size. Let's say four here. Um just so
that it's a factor of two still. Well,
why does that happen? Okay. Well, let's
say that we're using a tile size of 256x
128. That's a pretty natural size. Um as
a fun fun fact, you know, the matrix
multiply units in these GPUs, they're
they're naturally operating on matrices
of roughly size 128. So 256 x 128 is a
is a very nice tile size, right? So that
means how many tiles are there? Well,
there's seven * 14 tiles, right? Because
we're dividing the dimension of the
matrix by the size of our tiles. That's
a total of 98 different tiles. Um and if
we increase this by one, well, you know,
we're going to have to round up each one
of our coordinates. And so we're going
to have a lot more tiles, 120 of them,
right? Um so we've increased the number
of tiles by quite a bit. Um, well, you
know what's going to happen is not only
did we significantly increase the tiles
and some of them have lower utilization,
which is bad, but actually even worse,
an A100 has 108 SMS, right? Um, and if I
if you go all the way back to kind of
the GPU execution model, right, SM can
can execute in parallel and they're kind
of the execution units. And so when you
have 98 SMS, they all go and run, right?
You can you can dispatch them all. All
the SM are running, you know, you got
great utilization. Once you go to 120 um
tiles now you've got more tiles than
SMS. So 108 of those will execute and
then you will go back and you'll say all
right I've got some more SMS at very
very low utilization you're going to
execute the remaining 12 and wait for
those to complete right and that's going
to be really bad. So if you look at your
utilization, you got good utilization
for a while, you'll drop off a cliff and
then you'll sort of finish up your job,
right? So this is something called wave
quantization. Um and so ideally your
tile sizes are either much bigger than
the number of SMS or you know they're
they're not like this where you're just
like barely over the SM and you've
caused this quantization uh sort of
error uh
additionally.
Cool. All right. I know this is this is
low-level details, but in many ways, you
know, I I've been saying through through
many classes that language models and
deep learning is attention to detail.
Um, and these kinds of attention to
detail is the things that allow people
to scale up LMS um to really really
large sizes and get great performance.
Um, so it's worth knowing even if you're
not a person that's going to do systems
engineering. So, what were the tricks,
right? Um, key ideas here. First one is
you got to reduce the amount of memory
accesses, right? So, there's lots of
ways to do it. You can do coalesing
right so that you're not you can sort of
reuse reads that you're getting for
free. Um you can do fusion so that you
know you can fuse multiple operations
together and avoid unnecessary reads and
writes. You can move memory to shared
memory. So you know even if you're going
to do reads they're going to be from
much faster memory. Um and that's going
to be sort of tiling tricks that you can
do. Um and then finally you can kind of
trade memory for other resources that
you do have right? So you can trade it
for compute which is going to be um
recomputation or you can trade it for
just numerical precision or stability
which is going to be quantization right
so there's lots of bags of tricks that
you have in order to get sort of
performance um out right so so there's
lots of things you can do um you just
have to be really mindful of kind of the
role that memory plays in the
performance of a GPU right that's kind
of the key thing to get the m the most
out cool any questions on on that before
I sort of move to the final part with
flash attention
Okay, good. All right, so now I'm going
to put it all together, right? Like I'm
going to try to make it so that all the
the tricks that I taught you aren't
these like random disconnected facts
about GPUs. They're kind of part of the
standard performance optimization
toolkit and flash attention and flash
attention 2 will hopefully teach you how
that all comes together to to build one
of the, you know, the foundations, I
guess, of modern high performance
transformers.
So um flash attention you know we know
that it dramatically accelerates
attention um and most of you probably
know that that's done through some CUDA
kernel magic um but maybe you don't know
all the details right so you know what
the the paper says is okay so there's
one part that's happening which is you
know you do attention on a unoptimized
you know pietorch transformer
implementation if you fuse the kernel
and you do some things you can get
significant significant speed ups um and
from the paper you know they say we
apply two established techniques
techniques tiling and recomputation to
overcome the technical challenge of
computing exact attention in sub
quadratic HBM accesses right so so it's
not sub quadratic you know computation
because you can't do that you have to
compute you know attention in general
but they're going to get subquadratic
accesses to the uh high bandwidth or
global memory right and so that's really
the key if your memory is the bottleneck
you know you want to make that not
quadratic so that at least you can pay
for quadratic cost with your compute
rather than with your memory
So just for a really quick recap, you
know, at this point you've implemented
attention many many times in many
classes. Um right, so it's going to be
three different matrix multiplies.
You've got a K, Q, and V with a soft max
in between. Um so the matrix multiplies
are pretty simple that can be, you know,
done with tiling. I've showed you
examples like that. And what's different
about attention? Well, there's a softmax
thing that's going to be the real tricky
bit. And then once we can deal with the
softmax um all of the sort of matrix
multiply things I was talking about will
just come into play. So um the matrix
multiply as I said before is exactly
what I taught you. So if you look at the
figure one from the flash attention
paper, this is really just a simple
tiled matrix multiply, right? You see,
you know, the the K matrix, the Q
matrix, you see it cut up into small
blocks, you know, small blocks of it are
being copied to SRAMM, they're being
multiplied, and then they're being, you
know, accumulate or they sent to the HBM
where you do soft maxes um and then you
multiply um with a V, right? So this is
all just really simple um in terms of
the KQV matrix multiply. But now we have
to think about the softmax, right? Like
what's going on with the
softmax. So the key thing here is the
softmax. Sorry, I'm going to I'm going
to roll back one step. So the issue with
the softmax. What's the problem with the
softmax? It's a global operation, right?
The softmax in an attention operates row
by row. You have to sum the entire row,
right? To compute sort of the sum
normalizing term of the softmax. And
that's very problematic. If I have
tiles, right, ideally I want to do
everything within the tiles, right? I
don't ever want to have to write back to
the big matrix. And so I need a softmax
that can be computed online within each
tile, right? I want to do as much
computation within each tile as
possible. So the key thing here is to uh
use what's called the online softmax. Um
and so what is that? If you have a
stream of values, right, normally the
batch version of the softmax, you take
all of your x1 through x of ns and you
would exponentiate them, sum them, and
you would divide them, right? That's
what you would do in your normal
softmax. And then you would, you know,
maybe compute the maximum value and you
subtract that in order to be able to
make this numerically stable, right? So
this is the the standard numerically
stable softmax on the the left side. Um,
so the online softmax, I've taken this
from from Mikallof and Gimmelstein in
2018. Um well you can sort of realize
that you can pull out um via sort of
like a telescoping some kind of an
argument um basically the current
running uh sort of normalizer term and
the current sort of top term of e to the
x i minus max of x k right so what
you're going to do is you're going to
maintain your current max that you've
seen over x1 through x of j which is my
current iteration and then I'm also
going to maintain sort of this uh
correction term if my max updated This
is going to basically correct my max and
then I'm going to add my sort of new
term over here. Right? So this d of j is
going to track online the top term of
this equation term two over here and
then you know at the end I can also then
compute the the normalizer and then sort
of get the normalized y of i that I want
right this d of v is itself sort of the
normalization term um that I need. So
the key thing here is that this can be
done online. I don't need the x1 through
x ofn up front. All I need need is sort
of the stream of x1 through xn. And
that's really key because I can now
compute the softmax tile by tile. Right?
Within each tile, I can run this
algorithm and that will let me compute
kind of the partial softmax for that
tile. And then I can sort of write back
if I need to all the components that I
sort of I'm keeping track of. And that's
all that I kind of need in order to do
this computation. Right? So I never have
to materialize the full um n squ matrix
in order to compute the
softmax. And so that's basically it. But
once you have that, you know, you've put
it all together and you can get the
forward pass um of flash attention. And
if you go and look at the flash
attention to paper, which is um going to
be a thing that we're going to ask you
to implement. So you you're going to be
following through kind of these these
steps here. Um you're going to see
exactly this idea. So first you're going
to have your your KQ matrix multiply and
this is going to be tiled. So these are
little tiled chunks and they're going to
be multiplied. And how am I going to
compute the softmax? Well, I'm going to
maintain sort of a running value of
these sort of exponentiated sums. And
then I'm going to keep incrementally
updating it and correcting for the
maximum terms. And by doing that I can
compute all the necessary quantities
kind of tile by tile sort of going from
one tile to another. and then just
multiply once again with tiles with V in
the end and that will give me sort of my
full soft max output right um yes so we
won't be able to compute that output
until we compute the like 2k
multiplication across all tiles right so
we do have to double back on each um so
the question was you can't compute this
until you you are done um with all the
tiles and so you have to double back um
on all the tiles um So you won't have
built up that denominator sum until you
see every tile. Um that's right. So so
you will have to before you can output
your softmax you will have to go through
all the tiles. This is correct. Um but
by let's say I do all the tiles once
right like I do all n squed tiles. Um at
that point I have all the components
that I need in order to directly output
the soft maps. At that point I don't
have to re do recomputation because I
have the normalizer terms already right
by going through each of these kind of
tiles. at the end of going through all
these tiles, I've built up, you know, L3
or L L of N, which is the sum of all of
the exponentiated terms. So, I already
have that in my sort of uh in my shared
memory for this last tile. And then that
allows me to exponentiate and divide and
then return all the
components. Okay. Um, so the backward
pass I'm not going to cover. um you can
do recomputation tile by tile which will
allow you to avoid storing the softmax
right remember you know I always want to
avoid storing anything that's of size n
squared and so here I've been sort of
clever with the tiles so that I don't
have to store any of the n squ
components when I'm computing for
example the softmax but in the backwards
pass if I store the activations that's
already something that's n squed sized
right so I don't want to store my n
squed activations I'm going to have to
recmp compute it on the fly tile by tile
when I do the backwards pass Right. So
that's a really key other trick that
they do um in order to to make the
backwards pass possible. But otherwise
it's fairly standard. It's really the
same thing as computing the gradients
just tile by tile and doing that
computation.
Um so okay that that brings us to the
end here. Um, hopefully you've kind of
seen how all of the pieces I talked
about about tiling and coalesing and
recomputation um, come together to to
give you uh, flash attention and all
these really cool things that make your
transformers go much faster. Um, so to
to you know recap for the whole lecture,
right? Hardware is kind of the thing
that has really powered all of the
language models that we have today. Um,
and so if you really want to leverage
your hardware, you have to understand
the low-level details. I think all the
systems advances really engage with a
lot of the the concepts that I taught
today. Um and the current GPU sort of
scaling, you know, that plot is really
the one you should remember. Um really
really incentivizes and encourages you
uh to think about memory movement,
right? The memory movement is the
bottleneck in all of this. And so you
don't want to just think about oh how do
I reduce the number of flops? That's
important too. Um really you really have
to think about okay, how do I make my
memory movements more efficient? Um and
then finally if you you know have to do
a certain amount of computation well to
optimize things the way to do it is to
optimize your data movement right to to
be able to avoid as much movement from
the the high bandwidth memory or the
global memory um as possible. You want
to reduce that and have everything in
the very very fast shared memory and
that leads to good performance um on
things like um flash attention. Um
thanks everyone.